(Music)
(موسيقى)
["Oedipus Rex"]
["الملك أوديب"]
["The Lion King"]
["الأسد الملك"]
["Titus"]
["تيتوس"]
["Frida"]
["فريدا"]
["The Magic Flute"]
["الناي السحري"]
["Across The Universe"]
["عبر الكون"]
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Julie Taymor: Thank you. Thank you very much.
جولي تايمور: شكراً, شكراً جزيلاً
That's a few samples of the theater, opera
هذه نماذج من المسرح والأوبرا
and films that I have done over the last 20 years.
والأفلام التي قمت بها خلال ال20 سنة الماضية
But what I'd like to begin with right now
ولكن ما أود أن ابدأ به الآن
is to take you back to a moment
هو الرجوع الى اللحظة
that I went through in Indonesia,
التي ذهبت فيها اٍلى اٍندونيسيا
which is a seminal moment in my life
والتي تعتبر لحظة تاريخية في حياتي
and, like all myths,
وككل الأساطير
these stories need to be retold
تحتاج هذه القصص لأن تُحكى
and told, lest we forget them.
وتُحكي, حتى لا ننساها
And when I'm in the turbulent times, as we know,
وكما نعرف , عندما أمر بأوقات عصيبة
that I am right now, through the crucible
كما أنا الآن مع مسرحية "البوتقة"
and the fire of transformation,
ونار التحول
which is what all of you do, actually.
وهو ,في الواقع, ما تفعلوه جميعكم
Anybody who creates knows there's that point where
أي شخص مبدع يعرف أن هناك مرحلة حيث
it hasn't quite become the phoenix or the burnt char.
لا يصبح كطائر الفينيق أو كالفحم المحترق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I am right there on the edge,
وانا هنا الآن على الحافة
which I'll tell you about, another story.
التي سأخبركم عنها قصة آخرى
I want to go back to Indonesia
أريد العودة لقصة اندونيسيا
where I was about 21, 22 years, a long time ago,
عندما كنت أبلغ حوالي22,21 سنة ,منذ فترة طويلة
on a fellowship.
كنت بمنحة جامعية
And I found myself, after two years there
وجدت نفسي, بعد عامين هناك
and performing and learning, on the island of Bali,
من الاداء والتعلم في جزيرة "بالي"
on the edge of a crater, Gunung Batur.
على حافة فوهة بركان, جونونج باتور
And I was in a village where there was
وكنت بقرية حيث كان هناك
an initiation ceremony for the young men,
طقوس احتفالية للشبان
a rite of passage.
طقوس عبور
Little did I know that it was mine as well.
ولم أكن أعلم أن هذا لي أيضاً
And as I sat in this temple square
وبينما انا جالسة بساحة المعبد
under this gigantic beringin banyan tree,
تحت شجرة بيرينجن بانيان العملاقة
in the dark, there was no electricity, just the full moon,
في الظلام. حيث لا يوجد أي اضاءة سوى اكتمال القمر
down in this empty square,
وتحت في ساحة المعبد هذه
and I heard the most beautiful sounds,
سمعت أجمل الأصوات
like a Charles Ives concert
كحفل لتشارلز ايفيز
as I listened to the gamelan music
واستمعت لموسيقى الغاميلان
from all the different villagers that came
من كل سكان القرى الآتية
for this once-every-five-years ceremony.
لهذا الاحتفال الذي يحدث مرة كل خمسة أعوام
And I thought I was alone in the dark under this tree.
أعتقدت أني بمفردي تحت هذه الشجرة
And all of a sudden, out of the dark,
وفجأة, خارجاً من الظلام
from the other end of the square,
من الجانب الآخر من الساحة
I saw the glint of mirrors lit by the moon.
رأيت لمعان المرايا العاكسة لضوء القمر
And these 20 old men who I'd seen before
وال20 رجل الذين رأيتهم من قبل
all of a sudden stood up in these full warrior costumes
وقفوا فجأةً في زي المحارب الكامل
with the headdress and the spears,
مع غطاء الرأس والرماح
and no one was in the square, and I was hidden in the shadows.
ولم يكن هناك أحداً بالساحة, كنت أتوارى في الظلال
No one was there, and they came out,
لم يكن هناك أحد , وخرجوا
and they did this incredible dance.
وقاموا بهذه الرقصة المذهلة
"Huhuhuhuhuhuhuhahahahaha."
"هوهوهوهوهوهوهوهاهاها"
And they moved their bodies and they came forward,
حركوا أجسادهم وأقتربوا للأمام
and the lights bounced off these costumes.
وارتدت الأضواء على هذه الأزياء
And I've been in theater since I was 11 years old,
كنت في المسرح منذ أن كنت 11 عام
and performing, creating, and I went,
اؤدي ,أبدع, وذهبت قائلة
"Who are they performing for
"لمن يؤدون
with these elaborate costumes,
بهذه الملابس الجيدة,
these extraordinary headdresses?"
وأغطية الرأس الغير عادية؟"
And I realized that they were performing for God,
ثم أدركت أنهم يؤدون للاله
whatever that means.
أياً كان ما يعنيه هذا.
But somehow, it didn't matter about the publicity.
لكن بطريقة ما. لا يهم الاعلان
There was no money involved.
لم يكن هناك استخدام للمال
It wasn't going to be written down. It was no news.
لم يكن يتم للكتابة عنه ولم يكن هناك أي أخبار
And there were these incredible artists
وكان هناك الفنانون المذهلون
that felt for me like an eternity as they performed.
فشعرت وكأنه الأبد بينما يؤدون
The next moment,
اللحظة التالية,
as soon as they finished and disappeared into the shadows,
بمجرد ان انتهوا واختفوا في الظلال
a young man with a propane lantern came on,
جاء شاب حاملاً مصباح بروبان
hung it up on a tree, set up a curtain.
علقه على شجرة وأنزل الستار
The village square was filled with hundreds of people.
امتلأت ساحة القرية بمئات الأشخاص
And they put on an opera all night long.
وغنوا أوبرا طوال الليل
Human beings needed the light.
البشر بحاجة للنور
They needed the light to see.
بحاجة للنور ليروا
So what I gained and gathered from this incredible,
لذلك ما اكتسبته وجمعته من هذه
seminal moment in my life as a young artist
اللحظة المذهلة الفارفة في حياتي كفنانة شابة
was that you must be true
أنك يجب أن تكون صادقاً
to what you believe as an artist all the way through,
في كل ما تؤمن به كفنان طوال الطريق
but you also have to be aware
ولكن عليك أن تكون أيضاً واعياً
that the audience is out there in our lives at this time,
أن هناك جمهور بحياتنا في هذا الوقت
and they also need the light.
ويحتاجون ايضاً للنور
And it's this incredible balance
وهذا هو التوازن المذهل
that I think that we walk
الذي اعتقد اننا نسير نحوه
when we are creating something that is breaking ground,
عندما نخلق شيئاً غير مألوفاً
that's trying to do something you've never seen before,
محاولين فعل شئ لم تره من قبل
that imaginary world
هذا العالم الخيالي
where you actually don't know where you're going to end up,
حيث لا تعلم الى أين ستنتهي
that's the fine line on the edge of a crater
وهذا هو الخط الجيد على حافة البركان
that I have walked my whole life.
الذي سرته طوال حياتي
What I would like to do now is to tell you
ما أوده الآن هو أخباركم
a little bit
قليلاً
about how I work. Let's take "The Lion King."
عن كيفية عملي. فلنأخذ " الأسد الملك" مثالاً
You saw many examples of my work up there,
لقد رأيتم أمثلة عديدة من عملي هناك
but it's one that people know.
ولكن هذا الذي يعرفه الناس
I start with the notion of the ideograph.
لقد بدأت بفكرة الايديوغرام
An ideograph is like a brush painting, a Japanese brush painting.
الايديوغرام يشبه فرشاة الرسم, فرشاة رسم يابانية.
Three strokes, you get the whole bamboo forest.
بثلاث ضربات تحصل على غابات الخيرزان
I go to the concept of "The Lion King"
جاءتني فكرة "الأسد الملك"
and I say, "What is the essence of it?
قائلة " ما خلاصة هذا؟
What is the abstraction?
ماهي الفكرة الغامضة؟
If I were to reduce this entire story
وان كان لي ان أختصرهذه القصة كاملة
into one image, what would it be?"
في صورة واحدة, ماذا كانت ستكون؟"
The circle. The circle. It's so obvious.
الدائرة.الدائرة. هذا واضح جداً
The circle of life. The circle of Mufasa's mask.
دائرة الحياة. دائرة قناع "موفاسا"
The circle that, when we come to Act II and there's a drought,
الدائرة التي نصل لها في الفصل الثاني حيث القحط
how do you express drought?
كيف تعبر عن القحط ؟
It's a circle of silk on the floor
دائرة من الحرير على الأرض
that disappears into the hole in the stage floor.
تختفي في حفرة في قاع الأرض
The circle of life comes in the wheels
دائرة الحياة تأتي ي صورة دوران
of the gazelles that leap.
الغزلان التي تقفز
And you see the mechanics.
وأنت ترى الآليات
And being a theater person, what I know and love about the theater
وكوني فنانة مسرحية, وما اعرفه واحبه بشأن المسرح
is that when the audience comes in
هو انه عندما يأتي الجمهور
and they suspend their disbelief,
ويؤجلوا عدم ايمانهم
when you see men walking or women walking
عندما ترى رجال أو نساء يسيرون
with a platter of grass on their heads,
بطبق من العشب فوق رؤوسهم
you know it's the savanna.
تعلم أنه السافانا
You don't question that.
فلا تشك في هذا
I love the apparent truth of theater.
أحب الحقيقة الواضحة في المسرح
I love that people are willing to fill in the blanks.
رغبة الناس في ملأ الفراغات
The audience is willing to say,
رغبة الجمهور في قول,
"Oh, I know that's not a real sun.
"أوه, أعلم أنها شمس غير حقيقية.
You took pieces of sticks.
أخذت مجموعة من العصي
You added silk to the bottom.
وضعت الحرير في أسفلهم
You suspended these pieces. You let it fall flat on the floor.
علقت هذه القطع وتركتها تقع على الأرض
And as it rises with the strings, I see that it's a sun.
وبينما ترتفع, رأيت انها الشمس
But the beauty of it is that it's just silk and sticks.
لكن الجمال في كونها مجرد عصى وحرير
And in a way, that is what makes it spiritual.
وبشكل ما هذا ما يجعله روحانياً
That's what moves you.
هذا ما يحركك
It's not the actual literal sunrise that's coming.
ليس شروق الشمس الفعلي الحرفي الذي يأتي
It's the art of it.
ولكن الفن فيه
So in the theater, as much as the story is critical
لذلك. في المسرح. كما أن القصة حرجة
and the book and the language,
والكتاب واللغة,
the telling of the story, how it's told,
طريقة القاء القصة,. كيف يتم نقلها,
the mechanics, the methods that you use,
أيضا فإن الآليات, الطرق المستخدمة,
is equal to the story itself.
تتساوى مع القصة نفسها
And I'm one who loves high tech and low tech.
أنا واحدة من محبي التكنولوجيا العالية والمنخفضة
So I could go from --
حتى أتمكن الذهاب من-
For instance, I'll show you some "Spider-Man" later,
على سبيل المثال، سوف اريكم بعض اللقطات من"الرجل العنكبوت" في وقت لاحق،
these incredible machines that move people along.
هذه الآلات العظيمة اللتي تنقل الناس.
But the fact is, without the dancer
ولكن في الحقيقة، من غير الراقص
who knows how to use his body and swing on those wires,
من يعرف كيف يستخدم جسده ويتأرجح على هذه الخيوط،
it's nothing.
إنه لا شيء.
So now I'm going to show you
فالآن سأوريكم
some clips from the other big project of my life this year,
بعض مقاطع من المشروع الكبير الآخر من حياتي هذه السنة،
"The Tempest."
"العاصفة".
It's a movie. I did "The Tempest" on a stage three times
إنه فلم, فعلت فلم "العاصفة" على المنصه ثلاث مرات
in the theater since 1984, '86,
في المسرح منذ عام 1984، 86،
and I love the play.
وأنا أحب المسرحية.
I did it always with a male Prospero.
أنا فعلت هذا دائماً مع بروسبيرو ذكر.
And all of a sudden, I thought,
وفجأة، فكرت،
"Well, who am I gonna get to play Prospero?
"حسنا، من الذي سيلعب دور بروسبيرو؟
Why not Helen Mirren? She's a great actor. Why not?"
لماذا لا هيلين ميرين؟ إنها ممثلة عظيمة, لماذا لا؟ "
And this material really did work for a woman equally as well.
وهذا الدور ينفع حقاً للمرأة، على قدم المساواة وكذلك.
So now, let's take a look at some of the images
الآن، دعونا نلقي نظرة على بعض الصور
from "The Tempest."
من "العاصفة".
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Video) Prospera: Hast thou, spirit, performed to the point the tempest that I bade thee?
(فيديو) بروسبيرا: يمتلك هو، روح، تؤدي إلى النقطة العاصفة و أنا المحتشدة إليك؟
Prospera: At first sight, they have changed eyes.
بروسبيرا: من النظرة الأولى، قد غيروا عيون.
Miranda: Do you love me?
ميراندا: هل تحبني؟
Ferdinand: Beyond all limit.
فرديناند: متجاوزاً كل حد.
HM: They are both in either's powers.
HM: كلاهما في قوى بعضهما.
Trinculo: Misery acquaints a man with strange bedfellows.
ترينكيلو: يعرف البؤس الرجل ذي الرفقاء الغرباء.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Looking for business, governor?
ابحث عن الأعمال التجارية، أيها الحاكم؟
Caliban: Hast thou not dropped from heaven?
كاليبان: ألم تسقط من السماء أنت ؟
Stephano: Out of the moon, I do assure thee.
ستيفانو: خارج من القمر، أؤكد لك.
Prospera: Caliban!
بروسبيرا: كاليبان!
Caliban: This island is mine.
كاليبان: هذه الجزيرة لي.
Prospera: For this, be sure, tonight thou shalt have cramps.
بروسبيرا: لهذا، يجب التأكد، الليلة أنت سوف تحصل على تشنجات.
Antonio: Here lies your brother no better than the earth he lies upon.
أنطونيو: وهنا يكمن أخيك و هو ليس أفضل من الأرض التي يكمن عليها.
Sebastian: Draw thy sword.
سيباستيان: أخرج السيف خاصتك.
And I, the king, shall love thee.
وأنا، الملك، سوف أحب هؤلاء.
Prospera: I will plague them all, even to roaring.
بروسبيرا: أنا سوف أجعلهم يعانون، سوف أعصف بهم.
Ariel: I have made you mad.
أرييل: لقد جعلتك تجن.
Prospera: We are such stuff as dreams are made on.
بروسبيرا: نحن مثل الأشياء التي تصنع منها الأحلام.
and our little life is rounded with a sleep.
و حياتنا الصغيرة محاطه بنومة .
(Music)
(موسيقى)
JT: Okay.
ج ت: حسنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I went from theater, doing "The Tempest"
فذهبت من المسرح، و فعلت "العاصفة"
on the stage in a very low-budget production
على المسرح في إنتاج ذا الميزانيات المنخفضة جداً
many years ago,
منذ سنوات عديدة،
and I love the play, and I also think
وأنا أحب المسرحية، وأعتقد أيضا
it's Shakespeare's last play,
أنها مسرحية شكسبير الأخيره،
and it really lends itself, as you can see, to cinema.
وأنها حقاً تعطي نفسها، كما ترون، للسينما.
But I'm just going to give you a little example about
ولكن أنا فقط سأعطيكم مثالاً صغيراً حول
how one stages it in theater
كيف تقوم بالعمل على المسرح
and then how one takes that same idea or story
ثم كيف تأخذ نفس الفكرة أو القصة
and moves it into cinema.
وتنقله إلى السينما.
The ideograph that I talked to you about before,
الإيديوجراف التي تحدثت إليكم عنه قبل،
what is it for "The Tempest"?
ما هو بالنسبة لـ "العاصفة"؟
What, if I were to boil it down,
ماذا لو اختزلته،
would be the one image that I could
وسيكون الصورة الواحدة التي يمكنني
hang my hat on for this?
تشبث قبعتي لها؟
And it was the sand castle,
وكانت القلعة الرملية،
the idea of nurture versus nature,
فكرة الرعاية مقابل الطبيعة،
that we build these civilizations --
أننا نبني هذه الحضارات-
she speaks about it at the end, Helen Mirren's Prospera --
تتحدث عن ذلك في النهاية، بروسبيرا, هيلين ميرين-
we build them, but under nature, under the grand tempest,
نحن نبنيها، لكن في ظل الطبيعة، تحت العاصفة الكبرى،
these cloud-capped towers, these gorgeous palaces will fade
هذه الأبراج المتوجة بالغيم، وسوف تتلاشى هذه القصور الرائعه
and there will -- leave not a rack behind.
وهناك سوف - لن تترك و لا حمالة.
So in the theater, I started the play,
ففي المسرح، بدأت المسرحيه،
it was a black sand rake, white cyc,
بمحراك أسود للرمال ، فتوة بيضاء،
and there was a little girl, Miranda, on the horizon,
وكانت هناك فتاة صغيرة، ميراندا، في الأفق،
building a drip castle, a sand castle.
بناء قلعة بالتنقيط، قلعة رمل.
And as she was there on the edge of that stage,
وكما كانت هناك على حافة تلك المنصه،
two stagehands all in black
كان هناك اثنين يرتدون السواد
with watering cans ran along the top
يحملون علب سقي و يركضون على طول الجزء العلوي
and started to pour water on the sand castle,
وبدأوا بصب الماء على قلعة الرمل،
and the sand castle started to drip and sink,
وبدأت القلعة الرملية في التنقيط و تغرق،
but before it did,
ولكن قبل أن تزول،
the audience saw the black-clad stagehands.
شاهد الجمهور الرجال المرتدي السواد.
The medium was apparent. It was banal. We saw it.
الوسيط كان جليا. كان عادياً. شاهدناه بأعيننا.
But as they started to pour the water,
ولكن عندما بدأوا يصبون الماء،
the light changed from showing you the black-clad stagehands
الضوء تغير من إظهار الرجال مرتدي السواد.
to focusing, this rough magic that we do in theater,
إلى التركيز، هذا السحر الخام الذي نقوم به في المسرح،
it focused right on the water itself.
ركز تماماً على الماء نفسه.
And all of a sudden, the audience's perspective changes.
وفجأة، تغير منظور الحضور.
It becomes something magically large.
لقد أصبح شيئا سحرياً كبيراً.
It becomes the rainstorm.
أصبح العاصفة الممطرة.
The masked actors, the puppeteers, they disappear,
الممثليين المقنعيين، محركي لدمى، لقد إختفوا،
and the audience makes that leap into this world,
و الجمهور قفز إلى هذا العالم،
into this imaginary world of "The Tempest" actually happening.
إلى عالم التخيلي للـ "العاصفة" وهي تحدث بالفعل.
Now the difference
الآن الفرق
when I went and did it in the cinema,
عندما ذهبت، وفعلت ذلك في السينما،
I started the actual movie
لقد بدأت الفيلم الفعلي
with a close-up of a sand castle, a black sand castle,
مع صورة مقربة للقلعه الرملية، قلعة رمال سوداء،
and what cinema can do is,
وما يمكن للسينما فعله،
by using camera, perspective,
باستخدام الكاميرا، والمنظور،
and also long shots and close-ups,
وأيضا لقطات طويلة ومقربة،
it started on a close-up of the sand castle,
فبدأ في صورة مقربه من قلعة الرمال،
and as it pulled away,
وكلما سحبت الكاميرا بعيداً،
you saw that it was a miniature sitting in the palm
رأيت أنها قلعة مصغره جالسه على راحة
of the girl's hands.
يد الفتاة.
And so I could play with the medium,
لذا فيمكنني أن العب مع الوسط،
and why I move from one medium to another
و لماذا انتقل من وسط إلى آخر
is to be able to do this.
هو أن أكون قادرة على القيام بهذا.
Now I'm going to take you to "Spider-Man."
الآن سأقوم بأخذكم إلى "الرجل العنكبوت".
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Video) Peter Parker: ♪ Standing on the precipice,
(فيديو) بيتر باركر: ♪ واقف على شفير الهاوية،
I can soar away from this. ♪
يمكنني أن ارتفع بعيداً عن هذا. ♪
JT: We're trying to do everything in live theater
ج ت: أننا نحاول أن نفعل كل شيء في المسرح مباشرة
that you can't do in two dimensions
الذي لا يمكنك فعله في الوسط ثنائي الأبعاد
in film and television.
في السينما والتلفزيون.
PP: ♪ Rise above yourself and take control. ♪
PP: ♪ ارتفع فوق نفسك و خذ السيطره. ♪
George Tsypin: We're looking at New York from a Spider-Man point of view.
جورج تسيبين: نحن ننظر إلى نيويورك من وجهة نظر الرجل العنكبوت.
Spider Man is not bound by gravity.
الرجل العنكبوت غير مرتبط بالجاذبية.
Manhattan in the show is not bound by gravity either.
مانهاتن في العرض ليست ملزمة بالجاذبية أيضاً.
PP: ♪ Be yourself and rise above it all. ♪
PP: ♪ كن نفسك وارتفع فوق كل شيء. ♪
Ensemble: ♪ Sock! Pow! ♪
إنسيمبل ♪! سوك! باو! ♪
♪ Slam! Scratch! ♪
سلاام ♪! سكراتش! ♪
Danny Ezralow: I don't want you to even think there's a choreographer.
داني ازرالوو: لا نريد منكم حتى ان تفكروا أن هناك مصمم رقصات.
It's real, what's happening.
ما يحدث ، إنه حقيقي.
I prefer you to see people moving,
أنا أفضل أن تشاهدوا الناس و هم يتحركون،
and you're going, "Whoa, what was that?"
وأنتم سوف تقولون، "قف، ما كان ذلك؟"
(Music)
(موسيقى)
JT: If I give enough movement in the sculpture,
ج ت: إذا أعطيت ما يكفي من الحركة في النحت،
and the actor moves their head, you feel like it's alive.
وحرّك الممثلوون رؤوسهم، ستشعرون بأن ذلك على قيد الحياة.
It's really comic book live. It's a comic book coming alive.
إنه حقاً كتاب هزلي حي. إنه كتاب هزلي تدب فيه الحياة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Bono: They're mythologies.
بونو: أنهم أساطير.
They're modern myths, these comic book heroes.
أنهم أساطير حديثة، أبطال الكتب الهزليه ،هؤلاء.
PP: ♪ They believe. ♪
PP: ♪ أنهم يعتقدون. ♪
(Screams)
(صرخات)
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
JT: Ohhhh. What was that?
ج ت: أوه. ماذا كان ذلك؟
Circus, rock 'n' roll, drama.
السيرك، روك آند رول، دراما.
What the hell are we doing up there on that stage?
ما هو بحق الجحيم الذي نفعله هناك على تلك المنصه؟
Well, one last story, very quickly.
حسن، قصة أخيرة، بسرعة كبيرة.
After I was in that village, I crossed the lake,
بعد أن كنت في تلك القرية، عبرت البحيرة،
and I saw that the volcano was erupting
ورأيت أن البركان كان يتفجر
on the other side, Gunung Batur,
على الجانب الآخر، جبل باتور،
and there was a dead volcano next to the live volcano.
وكان هناك بركان ميت بجوار البركان الحي.
I didn't think I'd be swallowed by the volcano,
لم أكن أعتقد أنه سوف يتم ابتلاعي من قبل البركان،
and I am here.
وأنا هنا.
But it's very easy to climb up, is it not?
ولكن من السهل جداً الصعود، أليس كذلك؟
You hold on to the roots,
يمكنك التمسك بالجذور،
you put your foot in the little rocks
يمكنك وضع قدمك في الصخور الصغيره
and climb up there, and you get to the top,
و تصعد إلى هناك، وتذهب إلى الأعلى،
and I was with a good friend who was an actor,
وكنت مع صديقي الذي كان ممثلاً،
and we said, "Let's go up there.
وقلنا، "دعنا نذهب إلى هناك.
Let's see if we can come close to the edge
دعنا نرى إذا يمكننا أن نقترب من حافة
of that live volcano."
ذلك البركان الحي ".
And we climbed up and we got to the very top,
ولقد صعدنا ووصلنا إلى أقصى ارتفاع،
and we're on the edge, on this precipice,
ونحن على الحافة، على حافة الهاوية، وهذا
Roland disappears into the sulfur smoke
رولاند إختفي في الدخان الكبريتي
at the volcano at the other end,
في البركان في الطرف الآخر،
and I'm up there alone
وأنا هناك وحدي
on this incredible precipice.
على شفير الهاوية.
Did you hear the lyrics?
هل سمعت الكلمات؟
I'm on the precipice looking down
وأنا على شفير الهاوية نظرت إلى الأسفل
into a dead volcano to my left.
إلى بركان ميت إلى يساري.
To my right is sheer shale. It's coming off.
على يميني هاويه صخريه.إنها تنزل.
I'm in thongs and sarongs. It was many years ago.
أنا ارتدي شبشب وعباءاة. كان ذلك منذ زمن طويل.
And no hiking boots.
لم ارتد احذية المشي لمسافات طويلة.
And he's disappeared, this mad French gypsy actor,
ولقد اختفى، هذا الممثل الغجري الفرنسي المجنون،
off in the smoke, and I realize,
في وسط الدخان، وأنا أدرك،
I can't go back the way that I've come. I can't.
لا يمكن العودة بالطريقة التي جئت بها. لا أستطيع.
So I throw away my camera. I throw away my thongs,
فرميت بعيداً الكاميرا. رميت بعيداً الشبشب،
and I looked at the line straight in front of me,
و نظرت إلى الخط المستقيم أمامي،
and I got down on all fours like a cat,
و مشيت على الأربع مثل القطط،
and I held with my knees to either side
وعقدت بركبتي إلى جانبي
of this line in front of me,
هذا الخط الذي أمامي،
for 30 yards or 30 feet, I don't know.
لـ 30 ياردة أو 30 قدما، لا أعرف.
The wind was massively blowing,
الرياح كانت تهب بقوه،
and the only way I could get to the other side
والطريقة الوحيدة التي يمكنني أن أصل بها إلى الجانب الآخر
was to look at the line straight in front of me.
كانت أن انظر إلى ذلك الخط المستقيم أمامي.
I know you've all been there.
وأنا أعلم أنكم جميعا مررتم بنفس موقفي.
I'm in the crucible right now.
وأنا الآن في البوتقة.
It's my trial by fire.
إنها نار تمحيصي.
It's my company's trials by fire.
إنها نار تمحيص شركتي.
We survive because our theme song is "Rise Above."
نحن على قيد الحياة لأن شعار أغنيتنا هو "ارتفع للأعلى."
Boy falls from the sky, rise above.
صبي يسقط من السماء، إرتفع للأعلى.
It's right there in the palm of both of our hands,
انه هناك في أكف أيدينا جميعا،
of all of my company's hands.
في أكف ايدي شركتي.
I have beautiful collaborators, and we as creators
لدى متعاونين جميلين، ونحن كمبدعين
only get there all together.
نصل إلى هنالك جميعاً معاً.
I know you understand that.
وأنا أعلم أنكم تفهمون ذلك.
And you just stay going forward,
و يمكنكم فقط مواصة المسير،
and then you see this extraordinary thing
ومن ثم يمكنكم رؤية هذا الشيء الاستثنائي
in front of your eyes.
ماثل أمام أعينكم.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)